南极洲
Antarctica.
地球上最冷 最恶劣 最偏远的大陆
The coldest, the harshest and the most remote continent on Earth.
曾几何时 人类从未涉足这片净土
No human being has ever descended into the depths that surround it...
直到如今
..Until now.
探索深海 和探索太空一样具有挑战性
The deep ocean is as challenging to explore as space.
对于人类而言 海洋的最深处
We know more about the surface of Mars
比火星的表面更神秘莫测
than we do about the deepest parts of our seas.
如今我们可以潜入这些未知的深处
Now we can dive these uncharted depths
去探索面纱下的秘密
to discover what secrets lie beneath.
沿着冰山墙面不断下潜
Sinking down beside the submerged wall of an iceberg,
我们进入了一个残酷的世界
we enter an unforgiving world.
这里的水是地球最冰冷的
These waters are the coldest on Earth.
随着下潜深度的增加 压强也愈加紧迫
As we descend into the deep, the pressure increases relentlessly.
来自海面上的光也逐渐消失
And the light from above all but disappears.
但不可思议的是
Yet, incredibly...
这里有生命存在
..There is life here.
我们曾认为 在极地海洋的深处
We might have expected that, deep beneath the surface of the polar seas,
应该是一片不毛之地
the waters would be truly barren.
但事实上 我们在这儿发现的生物多到令人难以想象
But in fact we find life here in unimaginable abundance.
丰裕多样的物种也不仅仅出现在南极水域
Nor is such great abundance confined to Antarctic waters.
洋流将世界各大海域的物种资源带向了深渊
Currents carry this richness into the depths of almost every ocean around the world.
令人惊讶的是 海洋深处
Astonishingly, in the deep sea,
藏匿着地球上最繁多的生命
there is more life than anywhere else on Earth.
阳光褪散 黑暗笼罩
The sunlight fades and the seas darken.
这是太平洋 200米的深处
Here in the Pacific, 200 metres down,
一个陌生的世界
we enter an alien world.
这里是暮光区
The Twilight Zone
永远处于昏暗的海域
a sea of eternal gloom.
这里遍布神奇的生物
There are strange creatures here.
这是一只火体虫
A pyrosome.
像一管两米长的大果冻
A tube of jelly two metres
游在上面的白鳍鲨与它相比
long that dwarfs a visitor from above -
像个小矮子
an oceanic whitetip shark.
经过层层过滤 只有极少量的光线 照射在这片深海处
Only a tiny amount of light filters down this far.
要想在这里生存 就必须充分利用每一丝光线
Survival here means making the most of every last glimmer.
这儿有条剑鱼
A swordfish.
它的眼睛像网球一样大
Its eyes are as big as tennis balls,
以便在这永恒昏暗中保持视力
to help it see in the perpetual dusk.
这是一只乌贼
A squid,
这种乌贼只在这里生活
but this is one that lives only here.
它的右眼看起来是永久向下的
Its right eye looks permanently downwards.
但它的左眼要大得多 并且被训练的能向上看
But its left eye is much bigger and trained upwards to detect the
这样就能探测到附近水域中猎物的轮廓
silhouettes of prey swimming nearer the surface.
难怪它被称为 斜眼乌贼
No wonder it's nicknamed "The cockeyed squid".
还有更神奇的
And even stranger.
这是管眼鱼
This is barreleye...
它有着一颗透明的脑袋
..A fish with a transparent head
里面满是胶状物 因此可以透过头部组织看到头骨
filled with jelly so that it can look up through its skull.
难以置信的是 这片暮光区 是海洋中90%鱼类的避难所
We now know that the Twilight Zone is a refuge for an incredible 90% of all fish in the ocean.
只有在晚上
Only at night
大量灯鱼才迁往海面
do vast shoals of lanternfish migrate to the surface
捕食微小的浮游生物
to feed on tiny plankton.
白天 它们就撤回于此
By day, they retreat back down here.
美洲大赤鱿
Humboldt squid.
身长两米 重达50千克
Two metres long and 50 kilos in weight.
像大多数鱿鱼一样 它们是贪婪的猎手
Like most squid, they're voracious hunters.
数量成百上千
There are hundreds of them.
它们发现了一群隐藏在
They've found a shoal of lanternfish,
南美洲海岸 水下800米处的灯鱼
hiding 800 metres down, off the coast of South America.
它们的触手上武装着强大的吸盘
Their tentacles are armed with powerful suckers
可以抓住猎物
with which they grab their prey.
若没有更多的灯鱼供它们捕获
And when there are no more lanternfish to be found...
它们便自相残杀
..They turn on each other.
这只鱿鱼捕获了一只小鱿鱼藏于触手中
This squid has caught a smaller one in its tentacles.
为了掩饰以得到片刻休憩
To hide its capture from the rest,
它会释放像烟幕一样的墨汁
it releases a smokescreen of black ink.
但一只更大的赤鱿挑衅
But then an even bigger one challenges it...
并偷走了它的的猎物
..And steals its catch.
暮光区
The Twilight Zone
是美洲大赤鱿最喜欢的猎场
is the Humboldt squid's favoured hunting ground.
他们很少深入到
They seldom go deeper...
下面的永恒黑暗水域
..Into the world of perpetual blackness below...
午夜区
..The Midnight Zone.
这是总水深三分之二处 阳光却步之地
Two thirds of a mile from the surface, beyond the reach the sun.
这暗无天日的水域
A giant black void,
比世界上所有栖息地的总和都大
larger than all the rest of the world's habitats combined.
这里的生物
There's life here...
非比寻常
..But not as we know it.
它们像外星人一样发出耀眼的光
Alien-like creatures produce dazzling displays of light.
几乎所有动物都需要吸引配偶并击退捕食者
Nearly all animals need to attract mates and repel predators.
这种光的语言在这里非常普遍
This language of light is so widespread here that these signals
这些信号可能是整个星球上
are probably the commonest form of communication
最常见的通讯形式
on the entire planet.
但我们对它们仍然所知甚少
And yet we still know little about them.
猎手们照亮自己
Hunters illuminate themselves,
以此吸引好奇的猎物
and by doing so attract inquisitive prey.
这是尖牙鱼
This is fangtooth.
它有着同体形鱼类中最大的牙齿
It has the largest teeth for its size of any fish.
尖牙鱼的头部和身体
There are pressure sensors
都具有压力传感器 以此探测
all over its head and body which can detect
周围游动的任何事物
anything moving in the surrounding water.
这是午夜区中最贪婪的鱼
It's the Midnight Zone's most voracious fish.
但猎物可以用光来分散其注意力
But prey use light as a distraction.
发光的墨水也可作为诱饵
A decoy of luminous ink.
在这片 漆黑深海中
Down here, in this blackness...
生物已摆脱时间的束缚
..Creatures live beyond the normal rules of time.
管水母群是永生不朽的
Siphonophores are virtually eternal.
它们不断地克隆自己
They repeatedly clone themselves...
有些群体最终长得比蓝鲸还长
..Some eventually growing longer than a blue whale.
这里像下雪一样
Down here it snows.
连续不断的有机碎片云
Continuous clouds of organic debris
从上面缓缓飘下
drift slowly down from above.
这是食物 所有滤食性动物
This is food, and a whole variety
都靠捕食它生存
of filter feeders depend on it.
水母
Jellyfish...
还有纤弱的海参
..And delicate sea cucumbers.
他们错过的1%的海洋雪
The 1% of marine snow they miss
最终落定海底
eventually settles on the sea floor.
经过几百万年的沉积 逐渐形成了一层厚厚的淤泥
Over millions of years it forms a layer of mud up to a mile thick.
这是一片空旷的平原
It's an empty plain that covers
覆盖了地球表面的一半
half the surface of our planet.
深海海床最初可能死气沉沉
The deep sea bed may at first appear lifeless...
但一种在泥浆中生活的独特生物 以此为家
..But it's home to a unique cast of mud-dwellers.
海蛤蟆
The sea toad.
一种有着巨大嘴巴和无比耐心的
It is an ambush predator with an enormous mouth...
伏击捕食者
..And infinite patience.
这种鱼在这里生活了太久
This fish has been living for so long here
连它的鳍都发生了变化
that its fins have changed
进化成了更实用的部位
into something more useful.
脚
Feet.
助它在海底行走移动
They help it shuffle about on the sea floor.
这是烙饼章鱼
The flapjack octopus.
它在淤泥上缓缓起舞
It hovers just above the surface of the mud
优雅从容地筛选虫子
as it delicately sifts through it, searching for worms.
但危险来临的瞬间 它也能如火箭般迅速躲闪
But it can jet away at the first sign of danger.
灰六鳃鲨和大白鲨一样大
A sixgill shark as big as a great white.
它可以整整一年不吃食物
It may not have eaten for an entire year.
它耗费最小的能量
It patrols the mud plains
在泥面平原上巡逻
using a minimum amount of energy.
上面 一具庞大的抹香鲸尸体
High above, the carcass of a huge
正在慢慢腐烂
sperm whale is slowly decaying.
这将是深海生物的财富
This will be a bonanza for the creatures of the deep.
整整30吨的食物
Food, 30 tonnes of it.
最终鲸落海底
Finally, it settles on the ocean floor...
它的存在很快被发现
..And its presence is soon detected.
灰六鳃鲨有异常敏锐的嗅觉
Sixgill sharks have an exceptionally acute sense of smell.
仅在鲸落地的25分钟后
Just 25 minutes after the whale's carcass arrives...
一条灰六腮鲨就发现了它
..A sixgill finds it.
每一口撕咬 都释放出血液 扩散开来
Each bite releases blood into the current.
此地有食物的消息迅速传播
The news that food is here spreads quickly.
两条更贪婪的灰六腮鲨到达
Two more ravenous sixgills arrive.
12小时内
Within 12 hours,
有七条巨鲨寻味前来
there are seven enormous sharks
它们互相推搡 争抢夺食
jostling with one another as they compete to tear off mouthfuls.
无人甘愿退让
No-one is prepared to back off.
24小时后 尸体的三分之一已被吃干抹净
24 hours later and a third of the carcass has gone.
第一条鲨鱼狼吞虎咽 势要饱餐一顿
The first arrival has gorged until it's completely full.
这顿饭足够维持它一整年
This single meal may be enough to sustain it for a whole year.
现在清理队到达了
Now the clean-up team arrives.
蜘蛛蟹的后肢钳着珊瑚
Spider crabs carrying coral in their hind legs,
大概以此伪装 从而免遭攻击
presumably as makeshift body armour.
这里也有石蟹
There are rock crabs here, too.
它们发现尸体的速度
They probably detected
可能和鲨鱼齐平
the carcass almost as soon as the sharks...
但它们行动缓慢
..But they can't move as fast.
一个月后 30多种食腐动物
A month on, and over 30 species of scavenger
正在瓜分最后的残羹剩饭
are clearing away the last edible fragments.
但现在它们也吸引了掠食者
But now the scavengers are attracting their own predators.
叉尾带鱼 习惯直立游泳
Scabbardfish, habitually swimming upright,
正一个个摘食它们
are picking them off one by one.
鲸鱼的牙齿开始脱落
Some of the whale's teeth have been dislodged
骨骼也开始散架
as the skeleton starts to fall apart.
四个月后 这里只剩下森森白骨
Four months later, there is nothing left but a few bones.
即便如此 这对某些生物来说
But even they are food...
也还是食物
..For something.
僵尸蠕虫
Zombie worms.
它们通过注射酸性物质 在尸骨钻孔
They tunnel into the bones by injecting acid...
从而获取遗留在骨中的少量脂肪
..And so reach the tiny amounts of fat that still remain there.
这可能需要几十年
It may take decades,
但最终骨头将变为碎屑
but eventually the last of the bones will crumble
整个30吨重的尸体
and the whole 30-tonne carcass
将被完全回收利用
will have been recycled.
这条鲸的陨落
A whale fall
是这片海底沙漠中短暂的绿洲
is a temporary oasis in the desert of the sea floor.
但这里也有永恒的绿洲
But there are permanent oases here, too.
泥上突出的岩石
Rocks projecting above the mud
为深海珊瑚的生长提供了场所
provide anchorage for deep-sea corals.
3.5英里深的水下
As far down as 3.5 miles,
深海中的珊瑚种类
there are more species of coral in the deep
比热带浅礁处的多
than on shallow tropical reefs.
没有阳光
Without sunlight,
他们只能依靠漂浮的食物存活
they rely solely on food drifting in the current.
一根纤毛需要一年的时间来生长
And they grow just a hair's breadth a year.
但其中一些可以活4000年
But some of them can live for 4,000 years.
就像它们的浅水亲属一样
They, like their shallow water relatives,
它们为其他生物提供家园
provide homes for all kinds of other creatures.
最美丽的海绵动物 就生长在珊瑚中间
Growing among the corals is one of the most beautiful of sponges.
这是维纳斯花篮
This is Venus' flower basket.
这些海绵生物有它们的房客
These sponges have lodgers.
俪虾
Shrimps.
礁石上捕食者虎视眈眈
There are plenty of predators on the reef,
所以这些俪虾很幸运
so the shrimps are fortunate.
当它们还在幼虫时期
Both this male and female
一雌一雄就被卷进海绵洞中
were swept into this sponge when they were tiny larvae,
海绵洞中的污物
along with the minute particles of food
便是它们的食物
on which the sponge feeds.
它们执子之手 与子偕老
They found each other and have been here ever since.
如今俪虾都长大了
Now they're full-grown
雌性俪虾也产卵了
and the female is carrying eggs.
一旦孵化出来
Once hatched, the larvae
幼虫就会从海绵的壁上游出来
will swim out through the sponge's walls.
但这对成年虾却不会迁移
But the shrimps will never leave.
它们出不来
They can't.
它们现在体形太大了 无法抽身离开
They are now far too big to go out the way they came in,
毫无疑问 它们在这里要比在礁石上
and no doubt they will live longer here than they would
四处游荡且无所庇护 活的更久
if they were wandering about on the reef unprotected.
不过 海绵这种简单的动物
But how one of the simplest of all animals, a sponge,
是如何建造出这样一个复杂的结构
is able to build such a complex structure,
为俪虾创造良好的生存环境
to the great benefit of the shrimps...
是一个谜
..Is a mystery...
更是一个奇迹
..And surely a marvel.
但如今 它们曾经无忧无虑的世界被夷为平地
But today their timeless world is being reduced to rubble.
人类的过度捕捞清空了上层水域
As overfishing empties the surface waters of the seas,
渔民的网开始伸向更深的水域
trawlers have started to ransack the deep.
数不尽的珊瑚礁
Now countless numbers of the reefs
在数千年的繁荣后
that have flourished here for millennia
毁于旦夕
lie in ruins.
随着时间的推移 海底的有机质慢慢分解
Over time, organic matter on the sea floor slowly decays...
释放出甲烷
..Producing methane.
在墨西哥湾
In the Gulf of Mexico
这些海底有机质会形成超咸液体
these eruptions also release a super-salty liquid.
浓盐水
Brine.
它们的盐度比普通海水浓上5倍
Five times heavier than seawater,
在海底积聚成一个个盐湖
it accumulates in great pools on the sea floor.
难以想象这样的画面
It's difficult to make sense of the sight.
在海底深处 遍布15米深的
A lake of concentrated saltwater, 15 metres deep
高浓度盐湖
at the bottom of the sea.
更奇怪的是 在这些咸水湖边
Around its margin, perhaps even more strangely,
居然有着繁茂的生物群
there is a profusion of life.
巨型贻贝 一种可以存活上百年的生物
Giant mussels, that can live and grow for a century or more,
在盐湖边密密麻麻的生长
pack tightly together,
周围还簇拥着以贻贝为食的俪虾和蹲龙虾
dwarfing the shrimps and squat lobsters that feed around them.
凶狠的食腐动物 海鳗
Cutthroat eels, scavengers,
也来到盐湖边
come to the shores of the
寻找口粮
brine lake in search of something edible.
有些海鳗甚至涉险进入到盐湖中
Some even venture into the brine.
在盐湖中待得太久
Spending too long in it
会让海鳗中毒性休克
can send an eel into toxic shock.
它只有期望尽快浮出盐湖
Its only hope is to rise above it.
这只海鳗成功逃脱了
It manages to escape.
而大多数动物则没有那么幸运
Others are not so lucky.
高浓度盐水腐蚀了他们的身体
The brine embalms their bodies...
盐湖边堆积着长时间以来
..And the casualties of decades
殉难的动物尸体
accumulate around the margins.
但洋底深处更为凶险
But parts of the deep are even more hostile.
纵横于此的 是离洋底数英里深的巨型裂缝
In places, gigantic cracks stretch for many miles across the ocean floor...
这些巨大峡谷直逼地心深处
..Canyons that plunge towards the centre of the Earth.
勘探船带回的扫描图像
Scans from survey vessels
为人们形象地重现
make it possible to graphically reconstruct
这一巨幅海底景观
an image of this vast submarine landscape.
位于太平洋的马里亚纳海沟 距离海底7英里
The deepest of all, at almost seven miles,
是迄今发现的最深的海沟
is the Mariana Trench in the Pacific Ocean.
即使珠穆拉玛峰都会隐没其中
Even Mount Everest could disappear inside it.
在这些海底峡谷
Down here, in these deep ravines,
人们曾经认为不可能有生命迹象
it was once thought that nothing whatever could possibly survive.
但事实证明即使是这里也有生物存在
But there is life even here...
海蛞蝓
..A kind of sea slug.
还有被戏称为 大洋猪 的动物
A so-called "Sea pig".
这些简单的生物以漂降到此的
They, and other simple creatures, manage to survive on the
极少数食物为食
minuscule amount of food that drifts down here.
与这只海星类似
Like this starfish,
它们可以承受住
they can withstand pressure
相当于50架巨型喷气机的压力
equivalent of 50 jumbo jets stacked on top of one another.
远程针式探头
A remote camera probe reveals
揭示出这些不可思议的发现
the most extraordinary discovery of all...
幽灵般的狮子鱼
..The ethereal snailfish.
距海底5英里深的峡谷里
At five miles down,
狮子鱼是迄今被发现的唯一鱼类
this is the deepest living fish so far discovered.
没想到狮子鱼这样
No-one imagined that an animal as
结构复杂的动物
complex as a fish
也可以在这样恶劣的环境下生存
could existin such extreme pressures.
从暮光区深入到午夜区
From the greatest depths to the uppermost limit of the Twilight Zone,
生活着的各式生物 似乎深海中并没有
it seems that there is nowhere in the deep sea
人们以为的死亡地带
where life of some kind can't survive.
于是人们开始认为地球上最早的生命
And we now think that the deep sea may well be
很可能起源于深海
where life on Earth began.
世界上地质特征最为丰富的海底深处
Here, in a world hidden within the greatest geological feature on Earth...
地球海洋的中央 隐藏着一座
..Running right down the middle of the world's oceans,
延绵横跨整个地球的水下山脉
an underwater mountain range, spanning the entire globe.
大洋中脊
The Mid-Ocean Ridge.
在南太平洋
In the South Pacific,
海底频受地质灾害
the ocean floor is being torn apart.
地球上超过四分之三的火山
Over three quarters of the planet's volcanic activity
在海底爆发
occurs in the deep...
而几乎所有的海底火山都分布在大洋中脊两侧
..Almost all of it along the Mid-Ocean Ridge.
伴随剧烈的地壳运动而来的是丰富的天然资源
But from this titanic violence come great riches.
浓烟和滚烫的海水从海底缝隙中涌出
Gases and scalding water gush up through the crevices.
凝结成大量矿物质 状如烟囱
Minerals condensing from these jets build up great chimneys...
谓之深海喷泉
hydrothermal vents.
就像这个被称为 哥斯拉 的30米高喷泉
This one, 30 metres tall, has been named Godzilla.
我们震惊地发现哥斯拉
Astonishingly, we now know
拥有着跟热带雨林一样繁杂的生物群
that they hold as much life as tropical rainforests.
甚至有些地方 一小平方米
In places, half a million individual animals
就能聚集数十万的各式生物
are crammed into a single square metre.
这些生物完全依靠微生物生存
They depend entirely for their food on bacteria.
而微生物便以溶解在热浪中的化学物质为食
And THEY feed on chemicals dissolved in the searingly hot fluid.
螃蟹会吃掉覆盖在它们壳上的细菌群
Crabs consume the bacterial mats that coat their shells.
有些动物则让这些菌群
Others maintain bacterial cultures
寄居在他们的身体里
actually within their bodies.
俪虾让菌群寄居在他们的口腔
Shrimps carry such cultures in their mouthparts,
但这也是一个十分危险的办法
but that is a strategy fraught with danger.
因为俪虾需要冒着随时被煮熟的危险
To provide sustenance for these microbes
冲进热水喷泉中
the shrimps must dash into the hot vents...
只为更好地为这些微生物提供食物
..And that risks being boiled alive.
过去十年间
In the last decade
人们发现的海底喷泉数量翻了一番
the number of hydrothermal vents discovered has doubled.
每一个喷泉都有它独立的生物群落
Every one has its own unique character and community.
但其中最重要的 应该是一座位于大西洋的海底喷泉
But perhaps the most important one of all is in the Atlantic.
名曰 失落之城
It has been named "The Lost City".
在它那高达60米的矿物塔里
Within its 60-metre towers,
上演着各种不可思议的画面
something truly extraordinary is taking place.
在这样一个极端的高温高压环境里
Under extremes of pressure and temperature, hydrocarbons -
不间断地生成生命的基本组成分子
the molecules that are the basic component of all living things -
碳氢化合物
are being created spontaneously.
事实上 许多科学家开始相信
Indeed, many scientists now believe
40亿年前 地球上最初的生命
that life on Earth may have begun
很可能就起源于
around a vent like this,
类似的海底喷泉
four billion years ago.
我们现在了解到在木星和土星的卫星上也有这样的深海
We now know that there are deep seas on the moons of Jupiter and Saturn.
如果地球上
If life can exist
如此极限环境里 都能有生物存在
under such extreme conditions down here,
那么远在地球之外的某处也会有生命诞生
then surely it could exist somewhere out there.
摄制组花了1000多小时潜入深海拍摄
The team spent more than 1,000 hours filming in the deep ocean,
通常乘坐探险潜艇 阿卢西亚号 和她的姐妹潜艇
mostly from the research vessel Alucia and her twin submersibles,
深海漫游者号 和  纳迪尔号
Deep Rover and Nadir.
拍摄南极洲是最壮志豪情的一次任务
Their most ambitious mission was to Antarctica,
摄制组希望在海底三分之二英尺下拍到生命
hoping to film life two thirds of a mile down,
这在以前从未尝试过
something never attempted before.
事实上我们不知道我们会发现什么
We honestly do not know what we're going to find down there.
我们只是去探索人类从未涉足之地
We're going to a place that has never been explored.
那里也许空空如也 也许生机勃勃
There could be nothing, there could be a carpet of life,
或者有意外之喜 谁知道呢
there could be anything in between. Who knows?
这是一项艰难的技术挑战
It's a huge technical challenge.
水温达到零下1.8摄氏度
The water temperature here can reach minus 1.8 Centigrade.
没有人知道潜水艇在这样的
No-one knows for sure how the subs will cope
恶劣环境下会怎样
with this extreme environment.
好 行 我把渗的水吸干 好了
OK. Right, I'm going to soak it up. OK.
第一次潜水半个小时后
Just half an hour into the very first dive,
潜水艇里发现了一个水洼
a puddle is forming on the floor of the sub.
奥尔拉确认它是渗进来的海水
Orla confirms it's seawater.
好的 收到 我尝试把水吸干
Yeah, Roger. I'm just try to soak up this puddle of water,
然后再看看是否还有进水
and then see if any more comes.
他们必须很快找到裂缝 修好它
They must find the leak and repair it fast.
- 需要我把椅子移一下吗 - 是的
- Are you going to knock that over my...? - Yeah.
你坐在已下沉450米深的小潜艇里 然后它进水了
You're at 450 metres in a small bubble and water's coming in.
回到海平面要花半个小时
That's a half an hour straight shot back up to the surface.
就会开始想
You're kind of thinking about,
是放弃还是继续下潜
"Are we going to fill up with water?
如果继续下潜的话 就必死无疑了
And if we are, there's no way out!"
是的
Yeah.
潜艇驾驶员在这个时候处理得很冷静
The sub pilots are well drilled for emergencies.
把那些东西清空 好的
Just pass them over. Yeah.
拉尔夫很快找到了裂缝并修好它
Ralph quickly finds the flood and fixes it.
整个过程他看起来不慌不忙
He made it all seem absolutely ordinary and normal and,
我搞定它了 不要担心
"I've got this covered, don't you worry,"
20分钟之内 他就搞定了
and within 20 minutes, he did.
南极海峡多姿多彩
The waters of the Antarctic Sound are potentially rich
也危机四伏
but also treacherous.
比如著名的 艾利冰山
The Sound is ominously known as "Iceberg Alley".
我们要找一个
We've got to find a place
可以让潜水艇自由升降
where we can get the submarines down and up
没有冰山碰撞和挡道的地方
safely without any icebergs coming along and bowling them over.
我感觉
I've got a feeling it's going
有点儿像太空侵略者游戏
to be a bit like a game of Space Invaders.
一立方米冰块重达一吨
A metre cube of ice weighs a tonne.
你似乎在小心翼翼地绕着一个球体碾磨
You start sort of grinding that around the sphere,
感觉很奇妙
it's delicate.
它就像一颗大彩蛋
It's like a big Faberge egg.
有一次下潜刚刚好
One dive brings them right
避过了潜艇顶上的冰山底
up to the underside face of an iceberg.
一会儿有小汽车大小的冰山
There are icebergs up there that are the size of a small car, and
一会儿又有海德公园一样的冰山
then there are icebergs up there that are the size of Hyde Park.
庞然巨物
Enormous.
这里的环境瞬息万变
Conditions here can change in an instant.
船长向潜艇发送无线电信息
The captain radios down to the subs
是 收到
Yeah, Roger that.
我们突然发现有两座冰山从冰架上崩落下来
We've currently got a couple of big icebergs coming down the channel,
而且它们似乎就快撞到一起了
and it looks like they're on a collision course.
两座冰山相撞的声音就在上方
The impact of two icebergs colliding overhead is clearly heard.
那就是冰山
That is ice.
冰山相撞的同时天气也变得糟糕
With icebergs colliding above and the weather turning fast,
潜艇很快被召回
the subs are quickly recalled.
摄制再次半途而废
Once again their efforts are thwarted.
终于 两周之后 天气变得晴好
Finally, after two weeks, conditions are just right.
摄制组又开始了深潜艾利冰山千米以下的探险
Once again the team attempt their 1,000-metre dive in Iceberg Alley.
下潜一个小时之后 他们才接近目标
An hour after leaving the surface they close in on their goal.
999.
控制中心 控制中心
Control, control.
纳蒂亚号
This is Nadir
到达底部 深度 1000米
on bottom, depth - one-zero-zero-zero metres.
收到 深度 1000米
Roger. Depth - 1,000 metres.
暂停 新纪录
Control out. New record!
人类第一次在南极洲深潜达1000米
First manned sub dive to 1,000 metres in Antarctica!
在深海底部 世界的尽头
At the bottom of the ocean, at the end of the world,
他们惊喜地发现了数以万计的生物群
the amount of life they find is astonishing.
他们同时震惊地发现
But they are equally astonished to find that,
离水面三分之二英里的地方
two thirds of a mile from the surface,
冰山仍具危险性
icebergs are still a danger.
石块因为冰山融化而掉进海里
Rocks can drop from them as they melt,
其中一块差点就砸到潜水艇上
and one lands right in front of the sub.
我想大多数潜水的人
I don't think many people who are diving subs
压根不会考虑被石块击中这种事
ever consider big lumps of rock landing on them.
这不是常见的风险项
It's, it's not your normal risk.
如果潜艇被这小石块击中
If it had hit the sphere,
顶多也就被稍微刮花一点
there's a good chance it would have put a nice scratch down it.
但如果这个石块是10到20吨重
If something of ten, 15, 20 tonnes had hit the sub,
那么潜水艇就毁了
it would completely destroy it.
但随着更深入的探索
But over the following dives
摄制组发现 也正是这些落石
the team learns it's these very drop stones
丰富了南极海底的生物群落
that enrich the Antarctic deep sea bed,
提供了生命所需的栖息之所
creating firm anchor points for life to thrive.
事实证明 想要欣赏海底深处繁盛的生命
Proof that the only way to fully appreciate the complexity and abundance of life in the deep
需要我们亲自去探索
is to go there ourselves.
下一次 我们去看看珊瑚礁
Next time, we travel to bustling coral reefs.
在这里 海底动物们则需要长途跋涉
Here, animals must go to extraordinary lengths
只为在这拥挤的空间里生存
to get ahead of the competition in these crowded cities.
解说：大卫·爱登堡
Translated by
PINASTER & LITTLE FIVE
翻译：嵩下小松树 & 小五
Supervised by
CHELLE
监制：杳杳
Proofreaded by
CANNAE & WILDER
校对：坎坎 歪二德
Compressed by
DREAM TEAVELER
压制：失梦旅行
Effected by
WILDER FROM SOU
特效：歪二德
我怕冰山砸到你们 我很担心
制片人:奥拉多尔蒂
詹姆斯 霍尼伯恩
执行制片人
巴克 泰勒
潜水队负责人
海  洋  深  处
蓝 色 星 球 Ⅱ 幕 后
蓝色星球Ⅱ
(海洋分为：阳光区、暮光区、午夜区)
(火体虫：磷海鞘属动物的通称,由上千单独个体组成的群体,而非单个生物)
(学名大鳍后肛鱼)
(水母个体之间通过"共肉"彼此相连)
(学名斑点单棘躄鱼 鮟鱇鱼的近亲)
(学名加利福尼亚面蛸 因触手张开时身形几近扁平神似烙饼而得名)
(灰六鳃鲨：六鳃鲨科中最大的一种 体长可达4.8米以上)
(中文名"偕老同穴" 日本人眼中永恒爱情的象征)
(马里亚纳海沟最深处海拔-11034米 珠峰海拔8844米)
(学名Scotoplanes 深海海参类棘皮动物)
(指 "木卫二" 和 "土卫六" ,后者海洋由高纯度液态甲烷组成)